Billy Byers Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Billy Byers Collection 1964-1980
ML31.B94
Byers, Billy, 1927-1996
1,167 items 35 containers 7 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Billy Byers was a composer, arranger, orchestrator, and musician (trombonist). The collection primarily contains full scores in Byers' hand. It represents a sampling of Byers' work as a composer, arranger, and orchestrator. The material shows the diverse styles, musical forces, and variety of performing venues in which he worked. The scores include works for recordings, live performances, television, and film; for small combos, big bands, and orchestras; and for singers of various styles, including pop, jazz, rock, rhythm and blues, and disco.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Byers, Billy, 1927-1996--Manuscripts.; Byers, Billy, 1927-1996.; Byers, Billy, 1927-1996.
Subjects
Arrangers (Musicians)--United States.; Composers--United States.; Motion picture music--Scores.; Music--Manuscripts--United States.; Popular music--United States.; Television music--Scores.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Edward Joffe; 1997
Gift; Yuriko Byers; 1997
Custodial History
In 1997, the Library of Congress was contacted by Edward Joffe, a musician and teacher at the New Jersey City University. Joffe had played in the orchestra for the last show that Billy Byers had orchestrated, Victor/Victoria, and the two had become friends in the last two years of Byers’ life. Joffe acquired several of Byers’ arrangements for Count Basie and Frank Sinatra when Byers had visited him, along with their mutual friend Bill Caiza. Caiza mentioned that he had acquired these scores when working for Byers’ primary copyist, Emile Charlap, and offered them back to Byers; instead, Byers suggested that he give them to Joffe. Eventually, Joffe felt that the scores should have a more permanent home where they would be available to generations of musicians and scholars; an inquiry at the Rodgers & Hammerstein Organization led to the suggestion that the Music Division of the Library of Congress would be an ideal place to house the collection. Joffe gave the scores to the Library, and assisted the Library in contacting Byers’ widow, Yuriko Byers, in the hopes that she would have additional scores that she might be willing to give to the Library as well.
Ms. Byers had several cartons of additional scores by her husband and was delighted to give them to the Library, also in 1997, to form the largest component of the Billy Byers Collection.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Billy Byers Collection is open to research.
Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Researchers may make single copies of items in the collection, but should be warned that various permissions are likely to be required in order to perform or record these arrangements and orchestrations.
Biographical Note
The following chronology is not complete, but rather represents highlights from Byers’ career–particularly items where agreement on dates and titles came from multiple sources. Most of Byers’ work as a musician is not included here, most notably the dozens of recordings on which he played the trombone. Distinctions between the term arranger and orchestrator are not always used consistently in various sources, so those differing designations here should not be taken as definitive.
Date Event
1927, May 1 Born William Mitchell Byers III in Los Angeles, Calif.
1933 Began piano lessons
1935 Began trombone lessons
1941 Onset of arthritis forced him to give up keyboard performance; began scoring films
1942-1943 Played with the Karl Kiffe’s Hollywood Canteen Kids Band
circa 1945 Graduated from Van Nuys High School; attended Harvard where he studied law for one year
1944-1945 Joined the Army Air Force
1949 Trombonist and arranger for Georgie Auld, Buddy Rich and Benny Goodman
circa 1950 Trombonist and arranger for Charlie Ventura and Teddy Powell; joined the staff of WMGM in New York; at 23 became arranger for Your Show of Shows television program
1950s Moved to Paris; musical director for American films made in France by United International Pictures; worked with Charles Aznavour
1955 Arranged Milt Hinton’s recording Basses Loaded
1956 Recorded Jazz on the Left Bank; arranged Coleman Hawkins’ recording The Hawk in Hi Fi; arranged Gene Krupa’s recording Drummer Man
1956-1957 Performed with Ray Ventura in France
1957 Composed film score for Le Grand bluff; returned to New York and joined a small radio band; active in the RCA Jazz Workshop
1959 Performed with Johnny Richards orchestra; arranged recording Eydie Gorme on Stage
1959-1961 Returned to Paris; composed film scores
1959-1960 Toured Europe in Quincy Jones’ orchestra for Harold Arlen’s blues opera Free and Easy
1960 Arranged Quincy Jones’ recording Swiss Radio Days Jazz Series, vol. 1
1960-1965 Quincy Jones’ assistant at Mercury Records; arranged music for a series of albums by Count Basie
1961 Taught Paul Newman to play trombone for film Paris Blues
1962 Arranged music for recordings Impressions of Duke Ellington and Peggy Lee’s Sugar ‘n Spice
1962, July 1 Marries Yuriko Saito
1963, July 9 Daughter Kimiko Byers was born
1963 Arranger/orchestrator for Count Basie’s recording More Hits of the 50's and 60's and for Frankly Basie: Count Basie Plays the Hits of Frank Sinatra; orchestrated recording The Beast in Me
1964 Orchestrated film The Pawnbroker
1965, July 27 Son Bryant Byers was born
1965 Arranged recordings Basie Picks the Winners and Chris Connor Sings Gentle Bossa Nova; arranger/conductor/orchestrator on Sarah Vaughan Sings the Mancini Songbook
1966 Moved to Malibu
1967 Composed film score for Young American
1968 Composed film score for Hawks and Doves
1969 Composed scores for the films Go for Croak, A Pair of Greenbacks and The Tijuana Toads; orchestrated film Music Box
1970 Composed film scores for Dopey Hacienda, Hop and Chop, and The Froggy, Froggy Duo; and television score for Hauser’s Memory
1971, Aug. 30 Daughter Michiko Byers was born
1972 Composed for television show Streets of San Francisco and film Flight to the Finish
1973 Musical director/conductor for Rod McKuen’s television show The Borrowers; composed for Barnaby Jones television program; orchestrator on film scores for The Sting and The Way We Were
1974 Toured Europe and Japan as trombonist with Frank Sinatra; musical director for the film Mame; composed film score for Moonchild
1975 Orchestrator for A Chorus Line; musical director for the film White Line Fever
1976 Orchestrated film score for Silent Movie; arranger/orchestrator on film score for Richard Rodgers–The Sound of His Music
1977 Musical director for television show Happy Birthday, Las Vegas
1978 Orchestrator/arranger for film Same Time Next Year and for television shows Ben Vereen and His Roots and Steve and Eydie Celebrate Irving Berlin
1979 Orchestrated stage show A New York Summer; composed score for television program Hanging In; arranger/conductor on Sarah Vaughan’s recording The Duke Ellington Songbook, vol. 1
1980 Orchestrated stage show Perfectly Frank; won Emmy Award for arranging television show Linda in Wonderland; won Emmy Award as principal arranger for television show Baryshnikov on Broadway
1981 Orchestrated stage shows Broadway Follies and Hello to Harvey; wins Emmy nomination as principal arranger for Walt Disney: One Man’s Dream
1982 Orchestrated A Doll’s Life for the stage; arranger/orchestrator for film Sophie’s Choice and television program Shirley MacLaine–Illusions “On the Outside Looking In”
1983 Orchestrated stage shows Chaplin and 5,6,7,8...Dance!; won Emmy nomination as principal arranger for television show Epcot Center: The Opening Celebration
1984 Conducted film score for Joyeuses Pâques a.k.a. Happy Easter; orchestrated opening ceremonies for the 1984 Olympic Games in Los Angeles; won Emmy Award as principal arranger for The Screen Actor’s Guild 50th Anniversary Celebration
1985 Orchestrated Grind for the stage; moved to Paris; conducted film score for Hors-la-loi a.k.a. Outlaws; created arrangements for the Lido de Paris!; Emmy Award as principal arranger for Christmas in Washington
1986 Conducted film scores for Every Time We Say Goodbye and Pirates; orchestrated the film Le Lieu du Crime
1987 Orchestrated Smile for the stage; orchestrated the film Les Innocents
1988 Orchestrated the film L’Ours a.k.a. The Bear
1990 Won Emmy Award as arranger for Julie Andrews in Concert on Great Performances; Emmy nomination as arranger for The 62nd Annual Academy Awards; arranged Mandy Patinkin’s recording Dress Casual
1991 Orchestrated The Will Rogers Follies for the stage; Emmy Award as principal arranger for The Walt Disney Company Presents “The American Teacher Awards; Emmy nomination as arranger for Christmas in Washington; arranger/conductor on Barry Manilow’s recording Showstoppers
1992 Arranged on the Boston Pops recording Unforgettable; orchestrator on Liza Minnelli’s recording Live from Radio City
1993 Arranger/conductor on Barbra Streisand’s recording Back to Broadway; arranger on the Boston Pops’ recording Night and Day; arranger on Frank Sinatra’s recording Duets; arranger on Michael Feinstein’s recording Forever; orchestrated The Goodbye Girl for the stage
1994 Arranger on Barbara Cook’s recording Live from London and Frank Sinatra’s recording Duets II
1995 Orchestrated Victor/Victoria for the stage; orchestrated Mandy Patinkin’s recording Oscar and Steve as well as Oh Brother for both stage and recording
1996 Orchestrated Julie Andrews’ recording Here I’ll Stay: The Words of Alan Jay Lerner and Leonard Bernstein’s New York; orchestrated portions of the recording The Life
1996, May 1 Died of cancer
1996, Aug. 27 Posthumously given the American Society of Music Arrangers and Composers Irwin Kostal Award
Scope and Content Note
This collection represents neither all nor most of Byers’ work as a composer, arranger and orchestrator, but provides a sampling of the diverse styles, musical forces, variety of performers and situations that he worked for and with. The scores here range from works for recordings, live performances, television shows, and film scores; for groups that range from small combos to big bands to orchestras of symphonic proportions; and for an eclectic array of singers, from pop to jazz to rock to rhythm and blues to disco; and even dancers. Missing here are any of Byers’ arrangements and orchestrations for Broadway musicals. It is hoped that someday this gap, too, will be filled by other collections in the Library.
Unless otherwise noted, all items in the Billy Byers Collection are full scores in Byers’ hand, and most of these are in ink on transparencies.
The collection came to the Library with most of the scores in envelopes marked in alphabetical order, usually marked with the name of a performer, but occasionally marked with the name of a project or a song title. We have retained that organization as closely as possible. In some cases, this arrangement results in scores for the same project ending up in different places. For instance, there were several envelopes marked “Steve and Eydie” which contained, among other things, scores for the television special Steve and Eydie Celebrate Irving Berlin. There were also scores for the same show in envelopes for the performers Carol Burnett and Sammy Davis Jr. Rather than put these scores together, we have kept them in the original order, but have included cross-references to help researchers find related materials. There are a few scores that may well have been inadvertently placed in the wrong envelopes before coming to the Library; for example, “Intro to 3 girls revised” which was included with the Ann-Margret materials. Unless there was additional evidence which convinced us that this was a mistake (such as an entry for this item appearing in another designation in the notebook inventorying the collection), we left it where it was found, but added a cross-reference–in this case to Three Girls Three.
In addition to song/work titles, other relevant information that appears on title pages is included in our listing following the colon. This information is often a date, a show title, the name of a record label, or some other piece of information that might help the researcher better identify the piece. Several of the scores include the designation “vaudeville.” We inquired of several people who had worked with Byers about the use of this term. The best guess was provided by the conductor Ian Fraser, who thought it indicated that fees for the arrangement had been calculated according to the scale charged for a live performance (original use); if the arrangement subsequently was used on a recording or as part of a television performance, an additional fee might be charged.
Because most of the collection is organized by the name of a performer, we have added a song index at the back of the finding aid. This index also includes songs we were able to identify among the many medleys (we were not able to identify all of them). It does not include the individual cue titles found in the film scores; instead, the major work titles for those films are indexed by “Miscellaneous cues.”
Mark Eden Horowitz, 2003
Organization of the Billy Byers Collection
The Billy Byers Collection is organized into one series:
Full Scores
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010561025
Container List
- Full Scores (Box 1-35)
  Arranged alphabetically by performer name or project title.
  - ABC 25th Anniversary
    - Batman; Batman fix, Arranged by Pete Myers and Lenny Stack. (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Donny & Marie, Arranged by Pete Myers.; Includes "I’m a little bit country." (Box-folder 1/2)
    - It’s a miracle, Arranged by Lenny Stack. (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Kiddie stars forever disco march, Arranged by Lenny Stack. (Box-folder 1/4)
    - My favorite things, Arranged by Pete Meyers. (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Singers medley, Arranged by Lenny Stack.; For Karen [Carpenter?], Ben, Toni [Tenille?].; Includes: "We’ve only just begun" and "Love will keep us together." (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Welk-Lennon Sisters medley, Arranged by Lenny Stack.; Includes: "Making our dreams come true;" "Love American style;" "Seventy-seven Sunset Strip;" "On the bandstand;" "Welcome back;" and "Happy days." (Box-folder 1/7)
    - You stepped out of a dream, Arranged by Pete Myers. (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Adams, Edie
    - Ain’t misbehavin,’ Oct. 10, 1966 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - I want to be happy (Box-folder 1/10)
    - I’m always chasing rainbows, Oct. 18, 1966 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Somewhere over the rainbow, Oct. 12, 1966 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Alberghetti, Anna Maria
    - Al di la: vaudeville 1979 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Medley #2: vaudeville 1976, Includes "Anema e core;" "O sole mio." (Box-folder 1/14)
    - What I did for love?: vaudeville 1979, Includes manuscript and an ozalid copy. (Box-folder 1/15-16)
  - American Express–79
    - Eatin’ out tonight, For Lena Horne. (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Andrews, Julie
    - Being alive: 76 vaudeville (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Chain of life insert, The: tv film ‘ 1975 Chain of life ending (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Everything old is new again (Box-folder 1/20)
    - Gershwin medley: vaudeville 1976, Includes "Swanee;" "‘S wonderful;" "Somebody loves me;" "I’ve got a crush on you;" "They can’t take that away from me;" "Embraceable you;" "How long has this been going on?;" "Our love is here to stay;" "Someone to watch over me;" "The man I love;" "I got plenty o’ nuttin’;" "It ain’t necessarily so;" "Summertime;" "Fascinating rhythm;" "I got rhythm;" "Strike up the band." (Box-folder 1/21)
    - I won’t last a day [without you]: vaudeville 76 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - If I ruled the world: special - film tv ‘ 1975, For Muppets. (Box-folder 1/23)
    - [I’ve grown] accustomed [to her face] bows: vaudeville 76 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Mancini medley: vaudeville ‘76, Includes "Whistling in the dark." (Box-folder 1/25)
    - One piece at a time: vaudeville 76 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - One to one–opening: tv film ‘ 1975 One to one b.g. #2 (intro to “You and me against the world”) (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Playtime b.g.: film tv– 1975 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - The secret of Christmas: CBS Records July 1973 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Sound of music opening /underscore (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Stars and stripes: tv film– 1975 (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Ann-Margret see also Radio City Music Hall Special
    - Aggies song: vaudeville 1980 Aggies song intro (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Christmas 1973, Includes "The Christmas song;" "Have yourself a merry little Christmas;" "White Christmas." (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Have yourself a merry little Christmas, For Ann-Margret and Gregory Peck. (Box-folder 2/3)
    - A heavy load (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Hollywood movie girls Hollywood movie girls-reprise (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Hurricane Sadie: nightclub 1978 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Lady in red part I: tv special Lady in red part III: tv special Lady in red part IV: tv special [Lady in red] Insert for part IV (arranged by Luther Henderson) Lady in red/He said little lady [Lady in red] After part V (arranged by Luther Henderson) (Box-folder 2/7)
    - M1-opening talk: Smith-Hemion - Ann Margret special 1979 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Rio [medley]: Smith-Hemion - tv special - 1979, Includes "I can’t give you anything but love;" "I go to Rio." (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Show biz medley: 1974, Includes "It’s one of those songs;" "Waitin’ for the Robert E. Lee;" "Nevertheless." (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Show boat sequence part II, Includes "Waitin’ for the Robert E. Lee;" "Life upon the wicked stage." (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Show boat part II, Includes "Can’t help lovin’ dat man;" "Swanee." (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Show boat pt 3: vaudeville 1977, Includes "Swanee." (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Six months long: Ann-Margret special (Box-folder 2/14)
    - TV concert section, Includes "I don’t know why, I just do;" "Come rain or come shine;" "How long has this been going on?" (Box-folder 2/15)
    - [Three] 3 girls revised, Intro to (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Tommy overture: vaudeville 1977 Tommy rescore (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Who are those guys?: 1980 vaudeville, For Raw Satin. (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Who taught her everything?: Ann-Margret special, For [George] Burns and [Jack] Benny. (Box-folder 2/19)
    - You never done it like that: vaudeville ‘78 (Box-folder 2/20)
    - [You’re gonna hear from me] You gotta hear from me (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Anton, Susan
    - Smile medley, Found in Ann-Margret envelope.; Includes "Smile;" "Can’t smile without you." (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Anytime, anyplace, anywhere: M-21, Originally from Miscellaneous cues [envelope 2]. (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Apple Pie: tv film 1978
    - Happy days are here again (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Arnaz, Desi see Minnelli, Liza
  - Astaire, Fred see Crosby, Bing
  - Ball, Lucille see Hope, Bob
  - Barnett, Eileen
    - I’m coming home again (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Make ‘em feel good (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Baryshnikov on Broadway
    - Ain’t misbehaving Ain’t misbehaving - new intro Ain’t misbehaving tag (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Broadway, closing billboard: 1980 - Smith/Hemion (Box-folder 3/7)
    - F. Ticket ballet part II F. Ticket ballet part III (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Guys and dolls: Smith Hemion1980 Guys and dolls intro: Mischa - Liza - Smith Hemion - live t.v. 1980 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - One, closing billboard (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Opening titles (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Show stoppers, intro: tv 1980 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Theatre land: Mischa and Liza - Smith Hemion Live t.v. 1980 Theatre land - run music Theatre land - long intro (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Basie, Count
    - At long last love: Reprise Records: Nov. 27, 1964 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Baby! I can change my mind: June 8, 1963, For Sonny Craver. (Box-folder 3/15)
    - [Call me] irresponsible (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Dooh-wah-diddy: Reprise Records Dec. 7, 1964, In envelope marked "Basie 65." (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Frisco: Jan. 23, 1963, In envelope marked "Basie 65." (Box-folder 3/18)
    - [He’s got the] whole world in his hands: Reprise Records Dec. 15, 1964, In envelope marked "Basie 65." (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Hey jealous lover: Verve Records March 25, 1963 (Box-folder 3/20)
    - Hucklebuck: Reprise Records Dec. 19, 1964 (Box-folder 3/21)
    - I’ll get by: Verve Records Jan. 1, 1965, In envelope marked "Basie 65." (Box-folder 3/22)
    - [I’ll] never smile again: Verve Records Feb. 28, 1963 (Box-folder 3/23)
    - [In] the wee small hours [of the morning]: April 6, 1963 (Box-folder 3/24)
    - My kind of town, In folder marked "Basie - Verve ‘63 (scores)." (Box-folder 3/25)
    - Nice and easy: Jan. 24, 1963 (Box-folder 3/26)
    - None but the lonely: Verve Records April 6, 1963 (Box-folder 3/27)
    - ‘O sole mio!: Nov. 16, 1964 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Pretty woman: Reprise Records, In envelope marked "Basie 65." (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Road to Mandalay: Verve Records March 1, 1963 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Saturday night: Verve Records March 3, 1963 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Shangri-la: Reprise Records Dec. 27, 1964 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Tennis show blues: July 14, 1963, For Sonny Craver. (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Tetanus sets in, Composed and arranged by Byers. (Box-folder 4/7)
    - That’s all: Verve Records Dec. 27, 1964 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - This love of mine: Verve Records March 16, 1963 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Walk right in: Reprise Records (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Watermelon man, In envelope marked "Basie 65." (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Your cheatin’ heart: Reprise Records Dec. 21, 1964, In envelope marked "Basie 65." (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Basie, Count and Frank Sinatra
    - All the way: June 20, 1965 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Call me irresponsible: June 24, 1965, Srrangement by Chris O’Farrill. (Box-folder 4/14)
    - The gal that got away (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Get me [to the church on time] (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Hello Dolly, Photocopy; arrangement probably by Quincy Jones. (Box-folder 4/17)
    - I can’t stop lovin’ you: Sinatra/Basie (Las Vegas), Photocopy; arrangement by Quincy Jones. (Box-folder 4/18)
    - I wish you love: Sinatra/Basie (Las Vegas), Photocopy; arrangement by Quincy Jones. (Box-folder 4/19)
    - [In the] wee small hours [of the morning]: June 20, 1965 (Box-folder 4/20)
    - It’s easy to remember: June 23, 1965 (Box-folder 4/21)
    - Lover come back to me: June 21, 1965 (Box-folder 4/22)
    - My kind of town: Sinatra/Basie (Las Vegas), Photocopy; arrangement by Quincy Jones. (Box-folder 4/23)
    - Street of dreams: June 24, 1965 (Box-folder 4/24)
    - Too marvelous for words: June 23, 1965, Arrangement by Chris O’Farrill. (Box-folder 4/25)
    - Where or when: June 20, 1965 (Box-folder 4/26)
    - You make me feel so young, Photocopy; arrangement probably by Quincy Jones. (Box-folder 4/27)
  - Bennett, Tony
    - Lullaby of Broadway: 1980 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Benny, Jack see Ann-Margret
  - Berlin, Irving see Steve and Eydie; Burnett, Carol; Davis Jr., Sammy
  - Berry, Chuck see also The Music Scene
    - Johnny B. Goode: The music scene (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Boogie fever (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Boogie shoes (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Boris Klein (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Boston Pops
    - After the love has gone: 1980, Reduced and bound photocopy. (Box-folder 33/1)
    - Give it all you got: 1980, Reduced and bound photocopy. (Box-folder 33/2)
    - Through the eyes of love: April 25, 1980, Reduced and bound photocopy. (Box-folder 33/3)